yo what's going on guys you're watching
JavaScript for beginners lesson 23 and
in this video we're going to take a
closer look at nan which stands for not
a number Wow alright gang so in the last
lesson you saw me do something like this
we had two variables and one was a
string with a number inside the string
and the other one was a pure number and
we loved the addition of these together
into the console we've got something
like this which was 75 and what's
happened is it's concatenate the two
together squash them together and given
us a string 75 right so what would
happen if I did multiplication instead
of addition I save that and refresh now
this time we're getting a number back
it's no longer a string and it's
multiplied these two things together so
what the hell is going on well
javascript is being useful here all
right and it's saying well you can't
multiply a string by a number but
because in this string I can see only a
number I'm going to help you out I'm
going to give you the result that you
want I'll multiply these two together
this one time and I'll give you that
number all right so that's just
JavaScript being helpful however if we
were to write Apple there right we can
up times five by Apple
yeah we could get five apples but that's
not the way JavaScript works that will
return us n a n which stands for not a
number it's basically saying to you
there that look whatever you've done
does not make sense I can't Times Apple
by five you know go back and fix your
code but this is also really useful for
checking whether certain values are a
number when they should be imagine this
scenario you've got a website and you've
worked out the meaning of life you have
a formula that can give you the meaning
of life right and you want users to come
onto your website and enter in some
details about themselves like that age
and all these details have to be numbers
because they're going into this formula
now you have one particular user that
takes upon themselves to entering a word
they're quite thick and basically Hill
height well what you're doing dude you
meant to enter a number so you want to
check whether he's entered a number and
not a word now we can use this n a n to
do that
all right so how would we do
well let's say these the values that
he's entered Apple and five and you just
want it to numbers so we need to do an
if statement to make sure that he's
entered two numbers right so we'll just
first of all check that a is a number so
we'll do our if statement this is our
code block and then this condition here
is going to check that a is in fact a
number right or rather we're going to
check that it's not a number and we can
do that by using a built in function of
JavaScript code is n a and remember this
stands for not a number
so we're saying is this not a number and
then we pass it in this variable here I
actually checking whether a is not a
number
so a is not a number so this will return
true okay quite confusing at first but
you'll get your head around it is a not
a number yes it's not a number so this
will return true so right here we'll do
something like console.log that ain't
even and number 50 all right so we're
telling them look going into a number
instead and we could say something like
else and then we'll work out the meaning
of life for them which believe it or not
is and then we'll concatenate the result
of a times B all right so let's look
through this again what we're saying is
we've got these two variables one of
them is a string it's not a number and
the other one is a number here we're
checking here is a not a number well
it's not a number so this is going to
return true so therefore we're going to
log this to the console that ain't even
a number and we spelled that wrong that
ain't even a number thicky however if
this was a number if this was five then
this would return false and we go down
here to the else statement and we'd say
the meaning of life is a times B very
simple guys let's refresh and we're
getting this message right here that
ain't even a number thicky all right so
let's change this to six and then
finally
the meaning of life is not for to two
guys is 30 it says her about there okay
so that is na n that's how we check
whether something is not a number and
there is a slightly easier way to do
this all round rather like a the
opposite way to do this we've seen that
the exclamation mark this thing here is
the not sign it's the negator operator
you know if we want to check something
to equal to we say that or if I want to
check something is not equal to we say
that now we can do that right here in
front of this statement and this they're
my friends becomes a double negative
all right this gets a little bit
confusing now we say it is a not a
number not or basically we want to check
that a is a number all right so this
basically reverses this statement so
this will now be false okay I know
that's hard to get your head around it
and it gets a little bit confusing but
believe me if we put that symbol there
we're saying okay is a not a number well
if we put a word in here then that would
be true because a is not a number and
then we're putting the negator operating
in front of it so we're reversing that
we're saying it not true which is false
okay so then we can switch these around
if we wanted to like this and that one
there there now technically there's no
real difference in the way we've done
this it's just that sometimes we don't
have an else statement we just have the
if statement and we want to put the
outcome here all right whoo so if you
have any questions about this whatsoever
feel free to comment down below
otherwise if you enjoyed these videos
please share subscribe or like I'll see
you guys in the next one