yo what's going on guys you're watching
JavaScript for beginners in lesson two
what is JavaScript that's coming up ah
alright so javascript is one of the
three core languages of websites now the
first one is HTML we've already seen
that it controls the structure of your
web page via HTML tags the second one is
CSS and this is more to do with the
presentation and design of your website
so you can change colors or change the
layout of your HTML in CSS and the third
one is JavaScript and JavaScript is
responsible for adding additional
behavior and interactivity to your
website to make it more interesting so
say for example you had a website with a
gallery on and in that gallery you want
users to be able to click to zoom in and
out of your images if you wanted to do
that then you my friends would probably
need JavaScript to do it now javascript
is a scripting language and many
programmers will just disregard it as a
scripting language not a programming
language and by that they mean it's
intentionally limited it doesn't have
the same features as other programming
languages such as C sharp C++ or Java in
there it can't communicate with
databases directly or file systems on a
computer among other things however its
intended purpose was to add
interactivity and to manipulate webpages
and for that my friends it's magnificent
now javascript is a client-side language
and essentially what that means is that
it runs on your computer in your browser
ok so when you type in a URL into your
browser that communicates with a server
it gets the information from the server
which brings it back to your computer in
the browser and displays it to you in
the form of a web page and that my
friends is a combination of HTML CSS and
probably JavaScript so all of those
three run on your browser on your
computer that's what it's meant by a
client-side language this is different
from other programming languages such as
Ruby on Rails PHP and ASP
on there they all run on a server so if
you go to a website running one of these
technologies you're typing the URL
communicate with the server the code
will run on the server and then send the
results of that code to your web browser
where it's displayed in a webpage so
javascript is client-side other
programming languages are server-side I
would say also not to rely on JavaScript
to add functionality to your website now
imagine you had a website and it sold
out in sanh line if you were to add some
kind of behavior to that website which
relied on JavaScript for example a user
couldn't add an item to their shopping
basket without JavaScript enabled then
that website is not very good you want
to make a website and it's going to be
accessible to everyone regardless of
whether they're using javascript or not
so make it without JavaScript first make
sure it runs completely fine on its own
and then add javascript to it to give it
that magic touch and the added
interactivity and finally I'm going to
say this javascript is not and has
nothing to do with Java Java is a
completely separate language and
JavaScript is just a name that was given
to it while Java was really popular so
they jumped on that bandwagon the
official name for javascript is Atma
script but we all refer to it as
JavaScript so that's about it for this
introduction to JavaScript to hope now
you've got a broad view of what it is
and what I can do in the next lesson
we're going to start using it to create
our first JavaScript program
I'll see you guys